let's move now to the requirements for virtualization
so in general we say that what we want from
the virtual machine or from the operating
system that is being run on top of an hypervisor
is that it acts like it was running directly
on the hardware
now what does this mean being a bit more
precise here? well we have at least three
requirements here one it's safety of course
we want the hypervisor to have full control
on the hardware that is being virtualized to the
different operating systems it needs to be also
something that achieves high fidelity
so what would happen in your program in your
process if you were running it on the read hardware
or directly on the hardware should be the
same that you get if you run it through a
virtual machine that is controlled by the hypervisor
and then of course you also need efficiency
you know at this point in the
course that whenever i mean the put a middleware in between
the real hardware and the processes like the
operating system is at the end of the day it can be very beneficial in terms
of the services it supports
but it's extremely important that it does
not introduce too many overheads that would
otherwise kill the benefits so one way could
be just to think of the hypervisor like
an interpreter so basically whenever the guest
operating system so the operating system
that is run by the hypervisor wants to execute
an instruction the hypervisor checks whether
it is safe to do that and in that case it
does it otherwise it simulates or emulates
that this thing is being done but actually does
something different so if the process
wants to run an increment the instruction
on a certain register that belongs to that
process itself ok go on the hypervisor
can just say do that if for example
he wants to disable all interrupts for a
while (the guest operating system) then of course
you can imagine that the hypervisor cannot
really do that because there are other operating
systems that might be waiting for interrupts
generated by the hardware so in that case it
then simulates that it's doing
that by not delivering interrupts
to the guest operating system but is not physically
disabling the interrupts in the real hardware
now in theory this works it is achieving
the safety and also the fidelity requirements because most likely
you can either run or simulate most of the
instructions that the operating
system or the processes running through the
operating system the guest operating system
are issuing it will not be efficient
we discussed since the beginning context
switches and all the cooperation between hardware
and operating system to make them have low overhead
you can imagine that every time the operating
system wants to run an instruction on behalf
of a process or just an instruction that belongs
to the operating system if you need the hypervisor
to check that isn't going to work
so our goal here is to have the hypervisor
or the virtual machine manager actually execute
let the operating system execute directly on the
hardware as much code as possible so what
is required both from the hypervisor and
the hardware to actually achieve this desired
goal of having the operating system the guest
operating system run on the hardware directly
as much as possible? well here we need to distinguish
between two types of instructions one are
the privileged instructions this I mentioned
them since the beginning of the course you
know that these can only be run by the operating
system
you have a
binary register the bit mode
and if you are in kernel mode then the privileged
instruction will not result in an interrupt
but if you are not it will generate an interrupt
and that's basically the mechanism the operating
system uses through the hardware to make sure
that user processes are not running instructions
that they should not but instead achieving
that through system calls that wake up the operating
system now we have another set of instructions
and these are the sensitive instructions
this can be run both in user and kernel mode
but their behavior might differ depending
on whether it's the user process that calls
them or the kernel/the operating system
that calls them if you have these two
sets of privileged and sensitive functions
the requirement to run guest operating systems
directly on the hardware as much
as possible is to have the set of sensitive
instructions as a subset of the privileged
instructions as shown in this picture other
alternatives in which they just overlap or
they are disjoint will not work
think about this why is this a requirement?
if you're running the guest operating system and
you know that whatever operation be it sensitive
or privileged will generate an interrupt because
sensitive operations are a subset of the privileged
ones and since all of them are privileged
they would generate an interrupt when the
guest operating system is trying to do something
independently or whether it's the user space
that is requesting something or the kernel
space you would always get an interrupt
so the hypervisor can always be waken up and
allowed to take a decision if you have this
alternative nonetheless it could be that a
sensitive instruction is executed
and this sensitive instruction if you were
running the real operating system the guest
operating system directly on the hardware this
sensitive instruction would be executed by
the operating system and you would have the
behavior that is associated to the operating
system
but since now it's the hypervisor who controls
the hardware and the guest operating system
can be seen as another user process these
instructions will be actually executed as a
user instruction so the problem here is that
you get a behavior from the hardware that is not
the one you want because who runs these
sensitive instructions
it's not really the operating system but it's
a process that stays on top of the hypervisor
so this is the very bare requirement you
need to fulfill if you want to run directly
your guest operating system on the real hardware as
much as possible
and this is since the year 2005
when it was introduced so again cooperation
between hardware and software and the operating
system it's the virtual
technology so you have this both in
Intel and AMD CPUs
so basically at the hardware you have a
bitmap that can be used by the hypervisor
to specify all the sensitive privileged instructions
that should generate an interrupt and wake up the
hypervisor so the hypervisor before giving
control to the operating system can use this
the guest operating system can use this bitmap
to make sure that all the instructions that
are important and need to be checked by the
hypervisor and might require some emulation
will actually generate an interrupt and wake
up the hypervisor
nonetheless virtual machines I mentioned
before virtualization is from the sixties
this hardware technology is from 2005 so there were
solutions before and actually the solutions
we had before are still being used and
this is known as binary translation
basically the idea is that the hypervisor
before running the guest operating system
directly on the hardware will check portions
of the instructions that are going to be executed
and compile them translate them into a new
version in which all unsafe input-output
so basically sensitive functions that will
behave differently depending on whether it's
the operating system or the user process that
calls them will generate a trap so you basically
take what you have to run the hypervisor takes
this and recompiles it in a different code
which is basically the original code with
unsafe I/O instructions changed in order to
wake up the hypervisor